Guide to the Martha Greenhouse Collection of Acting Union Records WAG.217
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Martha Greenhouse Collection of Acting Union Records
1943-1997
1968-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Greenhouse, Martha
WAG.217
8 Linear Feet in 16 manuscript boxes.
Martha Greenhouse (1921-2013) was a New York stage, film, and television actor who was an active member and leader of unions for actors, most notably the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) and the Screen Actors Guild (SAG). Greenhouse joined the American Federation of Radio Artists, the predecessor to AFTRA, in 1941 and SAG in 1955. This collection spans from 1943 to 1997; the bulk of the materials were created between 1968 and 1992. The collection includes records collected by Martha Greenhouse in the course of her time as a member and leader of AFTRA, SAG, and other unions for actors. The majority of the records are union meeting minutes, agendas, memoranda, and communications to union members, committees, or officers. The collection also includes governing documents, contracts, financial statements, press releases and clippings, and union member benefits. There are also clippings and other records related to the larger labor movement during the years Greenhouse was active.
Scope and Contents
This collection spans from 1943 to 1997; the bulk of the materials were created between 1968 and 1992. The collection includes records collected by Martha Greenhouse in the course of her time as a member and leader of American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), the Screen Actors Guild (SAG), and other unions for actors including the Actors Equity Association (AEA) and the Associated Actors and Artistes of America (AAAA). Greenhouse was active in AFTRA, specifically the New York Local, for the duration of her career from the 1950s to the 1990s, and especially in the 1970s and 1980s. During the 1980s and 1990s she held leadership roles in SAG as well.
This collection includes national, regional, and local board meeting minutes; agendas; memoranda; and communications to union members, committees, or officers from both AFTRA and SAG. It also includes governing documents, contracts, financial statements, union member benefits, and press releases and clippings from both unions. There are files demonstrating the campaign to merge SAG and AFTRA during the 1970s and 1980s as well as records that show that both unions worked together to jointly negotiate contracts well before they merged in 2012. Some documents include notes and annotations written by Greenhouse.
Greenhouse also collected press clippings, correspondence, and other records that related to the general labor movement over the course of her career. These materials include records about women and minorities in both unions and the acting profession, news about strikes and boycotts initiated by other unions such as the Association of Flight Attendants and the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, labor-related legislation on the state and federal level, and labor studies.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Martha Greenhouse, 2002. The accession number associated with this gift is 2002.038.
Arrangement
Materials have been grouped together by topic.
Biographical
Martha Greenhouse (1921-2013) was a New York stage, film, and television actor known for her roles in the films The Stepford Wives, Bananas, and Daniel; television shows including Law & Order, The Jackie Gleason Show, and Love is a Many Splendored Thing; and stage productions including the original production of Rogers and Hammerstein's Cinderella.
Greenhouse was an active member and leader of unions for actors, most notably the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) and the Screen Actors Guild (SAG) which she joined in 1941 and 1955 respectively. She was also a member of Actors Equity Association (AEA) and the Associated Actors and Artistes of America (AAAA). She served as the president of AFTRA's New York Local from 1977-1982, represented the New York Local at national conventions, and served on AFTRA committees at both the local and national level. Greenhouse served two terms on SAG's National Board from 1981-1987, was active in the SAG New York Branch, and served on national and local SAG committees as well.
Greenhouse was in favor of the merger of SAG and AFTRA and advocated for it throughout the late 1970s and the 1980s. The two unions officially merged in 2012 to become SAG-AFTRA. She was recognized for her service to AFTRA and received the Founder's Award, the George Heller Gold Card, and the New York Local's Ken Harvey Award.
Related Archival Materials
For more information about AFTRA please see the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) National Office Records (WAG.281) and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA), New York Local Records (WAG.282).
For more information about SAG please see the Screen Actors Guild New York Branch Records (WAG.178).
Actors -- Labor unions -- United States.; Actors -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Women labor leaders -- New York (State) -- New York; Women in the labor movement -- United States; Women labor union members -- New York (N.Y.); Greenhouse, Martha; SAG-AFTRA (Organization); Screen Actors Guild; Screen Actors Guild. New York Branch; American Federation of Television and Radio Artists; AFL-CIO
- AFTRA--Articles of Agreement and Constitution, 1977-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- AFTRA--Contracts, 1967-1991 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
- AFTRA--Press Releases, 1971-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- AFTRA--Press Clippings, 1970-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- AFTRA--Newsletters, 1988-1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- AFTRA--Benefits, 1958-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- AFTRA-Alcohol Abuse Treatment, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- AFTRA--Welfare and Pension Trusts Report, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- AFTRA--Financial Records, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- AFTRA--Waiver Requests, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- AFTRA--Don Kennedy, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- AFTRA--National Board of Directors, 1969-1997 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
- AFTRA--National Convention, 1959-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
- AFTRA--National Committees, 1969-1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- AFTRA--New Electronic Devices, Wages, and Conditions Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- AFTRA--Eastern Section, 1968-1992 (Box 5, Folder 1-5, Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- AFTRA--Central/Eastern Section, 1987-1993 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
- AFTRA--Central Section, 1970-1991 (Box 6, Folder 5-6, Box 7, Folder 1)
- AFTRA-Western Section, 1970-1992 (Box 7, Folder 2-5)
- AFTRA-- New York Local Board of Directors, 1965-1997 (Box 7, Folder 6, Box 8, Folder 1-5, Box 9, Folder 1-3)
- AFTRA--New York Local Directors and Officers, 1968-1997 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- AFTRA--New York Local National Convention Delegates, 1970-1995 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- AFTRA--New York Local Executive Committee, 1970-1997 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- AFTRA--New York Local Nominating Committee, 1970-1997 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- AFTRA--New York Local Caucuses, 1973-1987 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- AFTRA--New York Local Equal Employment Opportunity Committee, 1977-1996 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- AFTRA-- New York Local Committees, 1970-1988 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- AFTRA--New York Local 50th Anniversary Celebration, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- AFTRA--New York Local Communications to members, 1959-1997 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- SAG--Constitution, 1983-1987 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- SAG-National Board of Directors, 1980-1987 (Box 10, Folder 3-5)
- SAG--National Board of Directors Eastern Section, 1986-1987 (Box 10, Folder 6, Box 11, Folder 1-3)
- SAG--National Board of Directors Western Section, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- SAG--National Board of Directors New York Section, 1977-1986 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- SAG--National Executive Committee, 1983-1987 (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
- SAG--New York Executive Committee, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- SAG--National Guild Government Review Committee, 1983-1987 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- SAG--Guild Government Review Committee New York Section, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- SAG--Ethnic Equal Employment Opportunity Committee, 1985-1990 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- SAG--National Committees, 1986-1996 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- SAG--Communications to all members, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- SAG--General Membership Meetings, 1971-1984, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 9, Box 13, Folder 1-2)
- SAG--New York Branch, 1971-1997 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- SAG--Accounting, 1985-1986 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- SAG--Budgets, 1983-1987 (Box 13, Folder 5-6)
- SAG--Regional Newsletters, 1986-1996 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- SAG--Press releases, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- SAG--Press clippings, 1986-1991 (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
- SAG--Contracts, 1959-1989 (Box 14, Folder 1-4)
- SAG--Elections, 1970-1987 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- SAG--Benefits, 1971-1989 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- SAG--Guild expenses, 1971-1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- SAG--Memoranda of Agreement, 1984-1989 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- SAG--Information Systems Project, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- SAG and AFTRA--Joint Action, 1977-1994 (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
- SAG and AFTRA--Joint Western Section Board of Directors, 1984-1986 (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Actor's Equity Association, 1943-1990 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Associated Actors and Artistes of America, 1987-1997 (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Joint Equality Committee, 1970-1972 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Minority Representation in Broadcasting, 1962-1985 (Box 15, Folder 8-9)
- Women in Labor, 1974-1991 (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Industrywide Labor Management Safety Committee, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 1)
- New York Labor Issues, 1972-1989 (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Labor Studies Programs, 1975-1982 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Labor Newsletters, 1978-1993 (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Legislation regarding labor, 1971-1987 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Satellite broadcasts, 1979-1987 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Big business and proposed boycots, 1971-1995 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- J. P. Stevens boycott, 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Flight Attendant Strike, 1988-1989 (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Farah Strike, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
- National Health Insurance, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Actors Federal Credit Union, 1976-1994 (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Equity League--Pension and Welfare Trusts, 1972-1989 (Box 16, Folder 13)
- Robert F. Wagner Archives, 1993-1994 (Box 16, Folder 14)